<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
   "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ELEMENT xi:include (xi:fallback?) >
<!ATTLIST xi:include
    xmlns:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href       CDATA      #REQUIRED
    parse      (xml|text) "xml"
    encoding   CDATA      #IMPLIED >
<!ELEMENT xi:fallback ANY>
<!ATTLIST xi:fallback
    xmlsn:xi   CDATA      #FIXED     "http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" >
<!ENTITY % local.chapter.class "| xi:include">
<!ENTITY % local.section.class "| xi:include">
]>

<!-- FILE        : Scalaness.xml
     SUBJECT     : Master document for the Scalaness documentation set.
     AUTHOR      : (C) Copyright 2013 by Peter C. Chapin <PChapin@vtc.vsc.edu>

This is the documentation for the Scalaness compiler. -->

<book status="draft">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Scalaness</title>
    <author>
      <firstname>Peter</firstname>
      <surname>Chapin</surname>
      <othername role="mi">C.</othername>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>University of Vermont</orgname>
        <orgdiv>Computer Science</orgdiv>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
    <copyright>
      <year>2013</year>
      <holder>Peter C. Chapin</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para> Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
        terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version published
        by the Free Software Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES,
        with the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST. A copy
        of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <!-- Do we really want to include this revision history now? -->
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>2013-09-01</date>
        <authorinitials>pcc</authorinitials>
        <revremark>This is a work in progress. Release 1.0 is scheduled for September
          2013.</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>
  <preface id="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Scalaness is an experimental fork of the Scala compiler that enables composition and
      generation of programs in embedded systems language nesC. Sensor network applications are
      increasing in complexity and can benefit from being dynamically reconfigured in order to
      optimize them based on current environmental factors. The Scalaness program writes a first
      stage program in a dialect of Scala that can specialize and compose nesC modules depending
      on the first stage program's inputs. The resulting nesC program is then deployed to the
      network. If conditions change the first stage program can be rerun to build a new, freshly
      optimized node-level program that can be redeployed.</para>

    <para>One unique feature of Scalaness is its type system. If a Scalaness program type checks
      every possible generated nesC program will also type check and thus compile successfully.
      This is important because we anticipate Scalaness programs being run in the field, for
      example on a base station or powerful hand-held device. The user of the Scalaness program
      will not be in a position to cope with type errors in the generated nesC, either due to
      inadequate development tools or insufficient programming skills. All nesC type errors are
      instead resolved by the Scalaness developer while the Scalaness program is being
      prepared.</para>

    <!-- Include disclaimer. -->

  </preface>

  <xi:include href="User.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="Design.xml"/>

  <!-- <bibliography> ... </bibliography> -->

</book>
